A Guide to the Papers of The World Affairs Council of Hampton Roads 1968-2000
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of the World Affairs Council of Hampton Roads 1968-2000
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 65
43 Hollinger Document Cases and one oversized box.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Raynor A.K. Taylor, President World Affairs Council, March 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
The World Affairs Council (WAC) of Greater Hampton Roads is a non-profit educational organization furnishing community services and programs unduplicated by other agencies in the area. The purpose of the WAC is to promote education, study, discussion, and understanding of world affairs, including all aspects of relations among peoples of the world, and of United States' foreign policy.
The foundations of the World Affairs Council (WAC) of Greater Hampton Roads were established by the Norfolk Chamber of Commerce, which sponsored the Norfolk Regional Foreign Policy Conference with the Department of State. This conference, held on November 21-22, 1968, attracted 450 business and government leaders from Virginia and North Carolina and 400 Virginia college students.
Beginning in January 1969, the Chamber sponsored a World Affairs Program Series in order to measure interest in the formation of World Affairs Council. As a result of the World Affairs Program Series, a nucleus of 150 persons, representing most of Hampton Road' cities, were identified as supporters for the establishment of a World Affairs Council.
This group elected a temporary executive committee and charged them with establishing WAC. After a series of public sessions to provide a guideline for the programming and activities of the Council, a charter was submitted to the State Corporation Commission and was validated on May 8, 1969.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of the World Affairs Council of Hampton Roads date from 1968 to 2006. The collection contains organizational and business related material, event flyers and programs, membership information, correspondence, and some photos. Items related to sister and parent organizations, including correspondence and event materials, are included.
Organization
The collection is broken down into the following series: Series I: 1960s; Series II: 1970s; Series III: 1980s; Series IV: 1990s; and Series V: 2000s. Each series is further broken down into sub-series by topic.
Series I: 1960s. This series relates to the World Affairs Council in the 1960s. Essentially, this series involves the formation of the Council and its first events in 1968 and 1969. This series is further broken down into the following sub-series: Sub-series A: Organization; Sub-series B: Business; Sub-series C: Correspondence; Sub-series D: Membership; Sub-series E: Programs and Events; and Sub-series F: Miscellaneous.
Sub-series A: Organization. This sub-series contains the original by-laws for the World Affairs Council and historical information about the organization, including a chronology of the formation of the Council.
Sub-series B: Business. This sub-series contains meeting announcements, minutes, board and officer nominations, and committee reports.
Sub-series C: Correspondence. This sub-series contains general correspondence of the World Affairs Council in 1968 and 1969, as well as correspondence related to its programs and advisory board.
Sub-series D: Membership. This sub-series contains World Affairs Council mailing lists from 1969 and membership invitations and brochures.
Sub-series E: Programs and Events. This sub-series contains information on programs and events hosted by the World Affairs Council in 1968 and 1969, and other business of the Program Committee. Material includes committee minutes, program flyers, event schedules, correspondence to speakers, and biographical material about speakers. Events include the Norfolk Foreign Policy Conference and the Norfolk Chamber of Commerce Speakers Series that originally developed an interest in forming the Council.
Sub-series F: Miscellaneous. This sub-series contains material that does not fit easily into the other sub-series. Material includes information on other world affairs councils, lists of films and publications, miscellaneous notes, and other such material.
Series II: 1970s. This series relates to the World Affairs Council in the 1970s. It is broken down into the following sub-series: Sub-series A: Organization; Sub-series B: Business; Sub-series C: Correspondence; Sub-series D: Membership; Sub-series E: Programs and Events; Sub-series F: Publicity and Publications; and Sub-series G: Miscellaneous.
Sub-series A: Organization. This sub-series contains by-laws, policies, fact sheets, and historical information that relate to the World Affairs Council in the 1970s.
Sub-series B: Business. This sub-series contains meeting announcements, minutes, committee reports, and related material from the 1970s.
Sub-series C: Correspondence. This sub-series contains World Affairs Council correspondence from the 1970s.
Sub-series D: Membership. This sub-series contains membership and mailing lists, membership invitations, brochures, and applications from the 1970s.
Sub-series E: Programs and Events. This sub-series contains flyers, schedules, and correspondence with speakers, biographic material about speakers, event schedules, and other material related to World Affairs Council events during the 1970s.
Sub-series F: Publicity and Publications. This sub-series contains a publicity handbook, press releases, and publications by or about the Council, newsletters, and newspaper clippings from the 1970s.
Sub-series G: Miscellaneous. This sub-series contains material that does not easily fit into the other sub-series. These include information on other world affairs councils, interest surveys, stationary, a media diplomatic list, and miscellaneous notes from the 1970s.
Series III: 1980s. This series relates to the World Affairs Council in the 1980s. It is broken down into the following sub-series: Sub-series A: Organization; Sub-series B: Business; Sub-series C: Correspondence; Sub-series D: Membership; Sub-series E: Programs and Events; Sub-series F: Budget and Finance; Sub-series G: Publicity and Publications; Sub-series H: Miscellaneous; and Sub-series I: Photos.
Sub-series A: Organization. This sub-series contains by-laws, articles of incorporation, historical information, fact sheets, and pages from a notebook on World Affairs Council business.
Sub-series B: Business. This sub-series contains meeting announcements and minutes, as well as advisory board and nominating committee business.
Sub-series C: Correspondence. This sub-series contains general correspondence for the World Affairs Council from 1980 to 1989.
Sub-series D: Membership. This sub-series contains address cards, membership lists and rosters, board rosters, information on corporate members, membership brochures, policies and dues information, business of the Membership Committee, a membership survey, and reports to the membership for the 1980s.
Sub-series E: Programs and Events. This sub-series contains event schedules, flyers, and programs, correspondence to speakers, and biographic material about speakers. 1980s events include speakers, discussion series, lectures, conferences, and the 1989 20th Anniversary celebration for the World Affairs Council of Hampton Roads.
Sub-series F: Budget and Finance. This sub-series contains draft agreements between the Hampton Roads Chamber of Commerce and WAC and scholarship fund information.
Sub-series G: Publicity and Publications. This sub-series contains the business of the publicity committee, press releases, material to be printed, and newspaper clippings from the 1980s.
Sub-series H: Miscellaneous. This sub-series contains material that doesn't easily fit into the other sub-series. Included in this section are notes, material from other world affairs councils, booklets and articles on Soviet - U.S. diplomacy, and other miscellaneous material.
Sub-series I: Photos. This sub-series contains photos from the U.S. - Soviet meeting at Old Dominion University on September 2, 1988.
Series IV: 1990s. This series relates to the World Affairs Council in the 1990s. It is further broken down into the following sub-series. Sub-series A: Organization; Sub-series B: Business; Sub-series C: Budget and Finance; Sub-series D: Programs and Events; Sub-series E: Membership; Sub-series F: Correspondence; and Sub-series G: Publicity and Publications; Sub-series H: Photos; and Sub-series I: Miscellaneous.
Sub-series A: Organization. This sub-series contains by-laws, information about incorporation, and a few sheets on the goals and purpose of the World Affairs Council.
Sub-series B: Business. This sub-series includes meeting announcements, minutes, and agendas, board and committee business, and strategic plans for the 1990s.
Sub-series C: Correspondence. This sub-series contains general correspondence of the World Affairs Council from 1990 to 1999.
Sub-series D: Membership. This sub-series contains membership lists and rosters from 1990 to 2000, lists of board, corporate, and special memberships, membership brochures and dues information, and reports to the membership from 1992 to 1998.
Sub-series E: Programs and Events. This sub-series contains event flyers, schedules, and programs, correspondence to speakers, biographic information on speakers, and other Program Committee business. Events include the annual Azalea Festival, the Corporate Luncheon Series, Great Decisions, the World Affairs Council monthly speaker series, and the World Affairs Council 25th Anniversary celebration.
Sub-series F: Budget and Finance. This sub-series contains tax and audit information.
Sub-series G: Publicity and Publications. This sub-series contains business of the publicity committee, newspaper clippings, the 1992 Great Decisions magazine, the 1994 Annual Report booklet for the Association of International Practical Training, and a 1994-95 newsletter for the Foreign Policy Association.
Sub-series H: Photos. This sub-series contains photos from 1990 events of the World Affairs Council at Old Dominion University and at the Norfolk Airport Hilton.
Sub-series I: Miscellaneous. This sub-series contains miscellaneous material from the 1990s that does not easily fit into other sub-series.
Series V: 2000s. This series relates to the World Affairs Council in the 2000s. It is further broken down into the following sub-series. Sub-series A: Organization; Sub-series B: Business; Sub-series C: Correspondence; Sub-series D: Membership; Sub-series E: Programs and Events; Sub-series F: Budget and Finance; Sub-series G: Publicity and Publications; Sub-series H: Miscellaneous; Sub-series I: Photos; and Sub-series J: Over-sized items.
Sub-series A: Organization. This sub-series contains the WAC Bylaws.
Sub-Series B: Business. Contains documents related to organizational business, including annual reports, notes on relocation, notes on archiving, meeting minutes, nominating committee correspondence, educational initiatives, and potential programs. Organized alphabetically.
Sub-series C: Correspondence. This sub-series contains general correspondence of the World Affairs Council.
Sub-series D: Membership. This sub-series contains membership lists and rosters from 2000s, directories, lists of board, corporate, and special memberships, membership brochures and dues information, and reports to the membership.
Sub-Series E: Programs and Events. This sub-series contains event flyers, schedules, and other papers related to programs, speakers, and events sponsored or participated in by WAC, including WorldQuest, Great Decisions, and the Azalea Festival. Includes speaker biographies, notes on potential programs, correspondence related to events, brochures, and venue information. Arranged chronologically.
Sub-series F: Budget and Finance. Contains budget, treasurer’s reports, grant applications, and information related to taxes, invoices, deposits, and audits. Spans 2001-06. Arranged in alphabetic, then chronological order.
Sub-series G: Publicity and Publications. Contains newspaper articles related to speakers hosted by WAC in 2000s, press releases, and newsletters.
Sub-series H: Miscellaneous. Contains information on WAC missions to Jordan, Cyprus, Taiwan, Tunisia, and Egypt, StatComm intelligence briefings, flyers from other councils, and notes from national events. Also includes letters of congratulations from significant statespersons including Colin Powell.
Sub-series I: Photos. Contains speaker headshots and photographs from some WAC events.
Sub-series J: Oversize. This sub-series contains over-sized items including a Proclamation of World Affairs Council of Great Hampton Roads Day and newspapers.
Contents List
- 1960s
  - Organization
    - Establishment of WAC undated (Box-folder 1:1)
    - By-laws 1960s (Box-folder 1:2)
    - History undated (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Historical 1969 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Business
    - WAC Sub-committee Report 1968 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Meeting Announcements 1969 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Minutes 1969 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - WAC V.I.P. Hosts Committee 1969 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Board Nominations undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence
    - WAC Correspondence General to 1969 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Program Correspondence 1969 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - WAC Advisory Board Correspondence 1969 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Membership
    - Mailing Lists 1960s (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Membership Letter undated (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Programs and Events
    - Chamber of Commerce Programs 1960s (Box-folder 1:15)
    - WAC Program - Event - Hoyt N. Ware, U.S. Department of State February 13, 1969 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - WAC Program - Event - Dr. Ernst Lemberger, Ambassador from Austria March 6, 1969 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - WAC Event - Panel led by Dr. E. Grant Meade September 16, 1969 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - WAC Program - Robert E. Culbertson, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Inter American Affairs October 9, 1969 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - WAC Event - Chief of Naval Operations Briefing Team December 4, 1969 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Foreign Policy Association 1969 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Norfolk Foreign Policy Conference (I) undated (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Norfolk Foreign Policy Conference (II) undated (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Misc. - Notes 1960s (Box-folder 2:7)
    - WAC Miscellaneous undated (Box-folder 2:8)
- 1970s
  - Organization
    - By-laws 1970s (Box-folder 2:9)
    - WAC Policy 1970s (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Fact Sheets and History 1970s (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Business
    - WAC Executive Committee 1970s (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Meeting Announcements 1970s (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Minutes 1970s (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Meetings 11/ 16/ 72 (Box-folder 2:15)
    - WAC Telephone Committee undated (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Nominating Committee 1970s (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Correspondence
    - General Correspondence 1970 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - General Correspondence 1971 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - General Correspondence 1972 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - General Correspondence 1973 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - General Correspondence 1974 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - General Correspondence 1976 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - General Correspondence 1977 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - General Correspondence 1978 (Box-folder 3:8)
    - General Correspondence 1979 (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Program Correspondence 1970s (Box-folder 3:10)
    - WAC Advisory Board Correspondence 1970s (Box-folder 3:11)
    - L.S. Parsons - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 3:12)
    - Correspondence - Bruce Powell undated (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Membership
    - Membership and Mailing Lists I 1970s (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Membership and Mailing Lists II 1970s (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Membership Brochures 1970s (Box-folder 3:16)
    - Membership Letters and Applications 1970s (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Programs and Events
    - Programs 1970s (Box-folder 4:1)
    - WAC Event - Leo J. Reddy, U.S. Department of State January 22, 1970 (Box-folder 4:2)
    - WAC Event - Corneliu Bogdan, Ambassador from Romania February 26, 1970 (Box-folder 4:3)
    - WAC Event - Hans Heinrich Noebel, Minister and Deputy Ambassador from Germany April 30, 1970 (Box-folder 4:4)
    - WAC Event - John S. Badeau, Director, Middle East Institute, Columbia University May 17, 1970 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - WAC Program - Dr. Ralph L. Powell, Professor of Far Eastern Studies, American University September 18, 1970 (Box-folder 4:6)
    - WAC Event - C. F. Baldwin, U.S. Ambassador to Malaysia October 29, 1970 (Box-folder 4:7)
    - WAC Event - In Nhel and Uk Someth, Cambodian Nationalists November 17, 1970 (Box-folder 4:8)
    - WAC Special Event - Cambodians November 17, 1970 (Box-folder 4:9)
    - WAC Event - Col. Robert L. Houston, President, Canada Japan Trade Association November 24, 1970 (Box-folder 4:10)
    - WAC Event - G. William Whitehurst, U.S. House of Representatives December 15, 1970 (Box-folder 4:11)
    - WAC Event - Vice Admiral J.E.L. Martin, Royal Navy, Deputy Supreme Allied Commander Atlantic January 12, 1971 (Box-folder 4:12)
    - WAC Event - Count Reginald de Warren, Counselor, Embassy of France February 18, 1971 (Box-folder 4:13)
    - WAC Event - Yousef Sharara, Counselor, Embassy of India March 9, 1971 (Box-folder 4:14)
    - WAC Event - Yousef H. Ben-Aharon, First Secretary, Embassy of Israel March 16, 1971 (Box-folder 4:15)
    - WAC Event - John S. Badeau, Director, Middle East Institute, Columbia University May 2, 1971 (Box-folder 4:16)
    - WAC Event - G. William Whitehurst, U.S. House of Representatives May 14, 1971 (Box-folder 4:17)
    - WAC Event - Dr. John Bennett, Vice President, World Affairs Council of Greater Hampton Roads September 26, 1972 (Box-folder 4:18)
    - Face to Face - Workshop - Citizen Education in World Affairs September 1972 (Box-folder 4:19)
    - WAC Event - Major Peter P. Marsh, British Army and Dr. Joseph Toland, Irish Physician October 25, 1972 (Box-folder 4:20)
    - WAC Program - Ambassador Felix Schnyder, Ambassador From Switzerland November 16, 1972 (Box-folder 4:21)
    - WAC Program - Brigadier General Robert Bennett, Senior Military Advisor, Canadian Section of the International Control Commission November 29, 1972 (Box-folder 4:22)
    - WAC Program - Dr. Norman A. Graebner, University of Virginia February. 6, 1973 (Box-folder 4:23)
    - WAC Program - Dr. George Grayson, College of William & Mary March 13, 1973 (Box-folder 4:24)
    - WAC Event - Mrs. Martha C. Mautner, U.S. Department of State October 17, 1973 (Box-folder 4:25)
    - WAC Event - International Group of Supreme Allied Command Atlantic Officers November 28, 1978 (Box-folder 4:26)
    - WAC Event - Baron Berndt von Staden, Ambassador from the Federal Republic of Germany January 18, 1979 (Box-folder 4:27)
    - WAC Event - Peter Riddleberger, World Bank May 2, 1979 (Box-folder 4:28)
    - WAC Event - Panel Discussion with Dr. Thomas Blossom and Dr. José Simón October 25, 1979 (Box-folder 4:29)
    - WAC Event - Ambassador Chai Zamin, Ambassador from People’s Republic of China December 4, 1979 (Box-folder 4:30)
  - Publicity and Publications
    - Publicity 1970s (Box-folder 4:31)
    - Publications - Printing undated (Box-folder 4:32)
    - Publications - Misc. undated (Box-folder 4:33)
    - WAC Newsletter 1970s (Box-folder 4:34)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1970s (Box-folder 4:35)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Interest Surveys and Recommendations 1970s (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Misc. - Notes 1970s (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Taxes 1970s (Box-folder 5:3)
    - World Affairs Councils 1970s (Box-folder 5:4)
- 1980s
  - Organization
    - By-laws I 1980s (Box-folder 5:5)
    - By-laws II 1980s (Box-folder 5:6)
    - Articles of Incorporation 1980s (Box-folder 5:7)
    - World Affairs Council Report to Members undated (Box-folder 5:8)
    - World Affairs Council Forms I undated (Box-folder 5:9)
    - World Affairs Council Forms II undated (Box-folder 5:10)
    - History and Facts undated (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Business
    - WAC Meeting Announcements 1980s (Box-folder 5:12)
    - WAC Minutes 1980 (Box-folder 5:13)
    - WAC Minutes 1981 (Box-folder 5:14)
    - WAC Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 5:15)
    - WAC Minutes 1983 (Box-folder 5:16)
    - WAC Minutes 1984 (Box-folder 6:1)
    - WAC Minutes and Agendas 1985 (Box-folder 6:2)
    - WAC Minutes 1986 (Box-folder 6:3)
    - WAC Minutes 1987 (Box-folder 6:4)
    - WAC Board Minutes and Notes 1985-87 (Box-folder 6:5)
    - WAC Minutes 1988 (Box-folder 6:6)
    - WAC Minutes 1989 (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Advisory Council undated (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Nominating Committee 1980s (Box-folder 6:9)
    - Membership Committee 1987-1988 (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Program Committee - Part I - Business 1980s (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Program Committee - Part II - Schedules 1980s (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Program Committee - Part III - Speakers 1980s (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Programming Survey 1986 (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence 1980-81 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Correspondence 1982-83 (Box-folder 7:1)
    - Correspondence 1984-85 (Box-folder 7:2)
    - Correspondence 1986 (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Correspondence 1987 (Box-folder 7:4)
    - Correspondence 1988-89 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Membership
    - Membership Policy undated (Box-folder 7:6)
    - Membership Committee undated (Box-folder 7:7)
    - Membership Drives 1980s (Box-folder 7:8)
    - Membership Survey undated (Box-folder 7:9)
    - Membership Brochures undated (Box-folder 7:10)
    - Board Roster 1980s (Box-folder 7:11)
    - Corporate Members I undated (Box-folder 7:12)
    - Corporate Members II undated (Box-folder 7:13)
    - Address Cards 1980s (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Members A-E undated (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Members F-J undated (Box-folder 8:2)
    - Members K-O undated (Box-folder 8:3)
    - Members P-S undated (Box-folder 8:4)
    - Members T-Z undated (Box-folder 8:5)
    - Membership Rosters & Lists 1980s (Box-folder 8:6)
    - Reports to the Membership 1980s (Box-folder 8:7)
    - Membership Dues 1980s (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Programs and Events
    - Spring Events 1980 (Box-folder 8:9)
    - WAC, ODU Visiting Scholar Program, The Center for Research in International April 22, 1980 (Box-folder 8:10)
    - WAC Event - Admiral Harry D. Train, Commander in Chief Atlantic Fleet June 9, 1980 (Box-folder 8:11)
    - WAC Event - Panel Discussion with Tom Reston, J. William Mittendorf and Allen Blachman September 23, 1980 (Box-folder 8:12)
    - WAC Event - Dr. Zbigniew Brzezinski, National Security Affairs Advisor to the President October 24, 1980 (Box-folder 8:13)
    - WAC Event - Panel Discussion with Alf Mapp, Robert Stern, Sandra Kelly and William Tazwell October 28, 1980 (Box-folder 8:14)
    - WAC Event - General Wenye Zheng, Air Attaché of the Peoples Republic of China November 21, 1980 (Box-folder 8:15)
    - WAC Event - Konsin C. Shah, Representative of the Coordinating Council of North American Affairs for the Peoples Republic of China in Taiwan December 16, 1980 (Box-folder 8:16)
    - WAC Event - Dr. Donald MacDonald, U.S. Department of State January 29, 1981 (Box-folder 8:17)
    - International Forum IX - China January 31, 1981 (Box-folder 8:18)
    - WAC Event - Dr. Terri McNamara, Deputy Assistant, Secretary of State February 18, 1981 (Box-folder 8:19)
    - WAC Event - David C. McGaffey, U.S. Department of State March 17, 1981 (Box-folder 8:20)
    - WAC Event - Frederick Stokeld, U.S. Chamber of Commerce April 9, 1981 (Box-folder 8:21)